A Register of the Gertrude King papers, 1942-1951
Hoover Institution Archives
Gertrude King papers, 1942-1951
1942-1949
2002C3
King, Gertrude
7 (2.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers primarily consist of correspondence, reports, memoranda, pamphlets, and serial issues, relating to internment of Japanese Americans during World War II, and to placement of Japanese-American students in colleges. Also includes records of the National Japanese American Student Relocation Council (NJASRC) and collected materials directly related to the Japanese American evacuation and relocation.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2002.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Thomas Ray Bodine Papers, 1941-1982, Hoover Institution Archives
John W. Nason Papers, 1921-2001, Hoover Institution Archives
National Japanese American Student Relocation Council Records, 1942-1946, Hoover Institution Archives
Separated Materials
The issues of the following publications have been separated from the collection due to duplication in the Hoover Institution Library: Communique;Denison Tribune; Granada Pioneer; Manzanar Free Press; Pacific Citizen; The Rohwer Outpost; Topaz Times; The Tulare News.
Historical Note
In the three months following the Japanese bombing of Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941 and the subsequent declaration of war on Japan and its allies, restrictions on Japanese Americans went into effect. Earlier restrictions first curtailed the activities of Japanese Americans, culminating with Executive Order #9066, where President Franklin Roosevelt authorized relocation of West Coast based Japanese Americans, immigrants and citizens alike. As a result, Japanese American students in the areas directly impacted by Executive Order #9066 were forced to withdraw from universities and colleges in which they were enrolled.
In response, a student relocation committee consisting of members from the national Young Men's and Young Women's Christian Association, West Coast college and university presidents, and other educators formed to assist Japanese American students already enrolled in higher education so that they could continue their studies. Within two months, the War Relocation Authority authorized the formation of a nationwide committee to address the issues facing Japanese American students that were pursuing or wished to pursue higher education. As a result, on May 29, 1942, the National Japanese American Student Relocation Council [NJASRC] officially formed.
Within the NJASRC, the front line of student relocation and assistance was the Permit Department. This department assisted students in securing permits to leave their assigned relocation center in order to attend school. The Permit Department also worked directly with the students and universities to place qualified students in schools best suited to their needs, within communities where they were least likely to face extreme prejudice and persecution.
One of the most vocal and active members of this department was supervisor Gertrude (Trudy) King (1916-1969). During her time with NJASRC (June 1942-April 1944), Trudy King made a lasting impression on her colleagues and the students she helped to relocate, as evidenced by the extensive correspondence with both sets of individuals during and following her time in the NJASRC, even past the point when the NJASRC closed its doors in June 30, 1946.
Additional information regarding Gertrude King and the NJASRC was obtained from From Concentration Camp to Campus: Japanese American Students and World War II, by Allan W. Austin, University of Illinois Press, ©2004.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Gertrude King Papers primarily consist of correspondence, reports, memoranda, pamphlets, and serial issues, relating to the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II, and to placement of Japanese-American students in colleges. The papers also include records of the National Japanese American Student Relocation Council (NJASRC) and collected materials directly related to the Japanese American evacuation and relocation.
Gertrude King joined the NJASRC less than two months after its formation on May 29, 1942 and remained until April 1944. During that time and in the years following, King maintained correspondence with several of her colleagues within the NJASRC and outside of it. The bulk of this collection consists of correspondence between King, her colleagues within the NJASRC, various individuals and groups that worked with NJASRC, colleges and universities, government organizations, relocation centers, and students. Along with correspondence both of an official and personal nature, the collection also includes several administrative and procedural documents for the NJASRC, including reports, college and student information lists, newsletters, memoranda, procedures, and personal notes regarding her work with the students directly and within the organization.
King also collected materials and documents relevant to the agencies she worked with her role in with NJASRC as well as materials related to the Japanese American evacuation and relocation during World War II and in the months immediately following.
The original order of the materials as they were when initially acquired was retained as much as possible. The final arrangement for the papers is as follows: Correspondence, National Japanese American Student Relocation Council Records, and Subject File and Collected Documents.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
National Japanese American Student Relocation Council.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1942-1951 (Box 1-3)
  Letters, both handwritten and typewritten primarily of a personal nature from relocated students other colleagues working with and part of the National Japanese American Student Relocation Council; includes postcards, greetings cards, and 1 envelope of photographs. Materials are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. If a last name is not available, arrangement was made by first name.
  - Andy, 1943 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Arthur, 1943 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Blumental-Bennett, Martha, 1942-1950 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Emlen, Betty, circa 1945-1947, undated (Folder 1: 4)
  - Cosgrave Margaret, circa 1942-1946, undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Endo, Yone, 1946-1948 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Fukushima, Tosh, 1946-1947 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Handa, Connie, circa 1946-1951 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Hata, Mari, 1948, undated (Folder 1: 9)
  - Hayashi, Terri, 1950, undated (Folder 1: 10)
  - Hiroaka, Chiyo, 1946-1949 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Inouye, Mary, 1946-1951, undated (Folder 1: 12)
  - Ishida, Gladys, 1948-1949, undated (Folder 1: 13)
  - Jay, circa 1944-1947 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Lee, Minnie, circa 1944-1947 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Maribel, circa 1947-1948 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Murase, Ken, 1950, undated (Folder 1: 17)
  - Megillian, Mary, 1944, 1950 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Nagatani, Kimi, 1943-1950 (Folder 1: 19-20)
  - Nishimoto, Katsuma, 1944-1945 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Okye, Betty, 1948, 1951 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Oshiki, Kaz, circa 1943-1948 (Folder 2: 2-3)
  - Ota, Lillian, circa 1943-1944 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Ota, Tets, 1945-1946 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Okamura, George, 1946 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Rhoads, Esther, 1942, 1948, undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - Saito, Sachio, 1944 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Sasaki, Hideo, 1946 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Shimizu, James, 1945 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Stevens, Ken and Stevens, Dottie, circa 1942-1947 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Stevenson, Bill, circa 1942-1947 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Sugihara, Ina, 1943 (Folder 2: 13)
  - Sugino, Art, 1944-1946 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Sugiyama, Bill, 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Takasugi, Nao, 1946 (Folder 2: 16)
  - Watanabe, Frank, circa 1943-1950, undated (Folder 2: 17-18)
  - Wilma, circa 1943 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Yamada, Mary, 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 20)
  - Yamada, Tamaichi, 1942; undated (Folder 2: 21)
  - Yamashita, Kay, circa 1944-1948 (Folder 2: 22)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1942-1949; undated (Folder 3: 1)
    Includes an envelope with greeting cards and postcards
- National Japanese American Student Relocation Council (NJASRC) Records, 1942-1949 (Box 3-6)
  Letters, administrative materials and forms, writings, lists, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, and documents generated for the organization and by the organization. The bulk of this material consists of correspondence within the organization and with entities working with the organization such as similar organization, local and state government offices, church groups, colleges and universities, and the students seeking relocation at all stages of the relocation process.
  Arranged into the following subseries, Internal Correspondence; General Correspondence; Colleges, Universities, and Academic Professionals Correspondence; Student Correspondence; Miscellany Correspondence; Materials and Procedures.
  - Internal Correspondence, circa 1942-1945 (Folder 3-4)
    - American Baptist Home Mission Society, 1942-1944 (Folder 3: 10)
    - American Friends Service Committee, 1942-1944 (Folder 3: 11)
    - Art Students League of New York, 1942-1943 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Churches and Other Religious Organizations, 1942-1943 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Friends General Conference, 1942-1943 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Local city, county, and state correspondence, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 1)
      Usually pertaining to community acceptance of incoming students
    - Haines, Ruth, 1942, undated (Folder 4: 2)
    - Morganroth, Ed, 1942 (Folder 4: 3)
    - Relocation Centers, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 4)
    - Relocation Centers, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 5)
      Includes information specifically pertaining to Manzanar and correspondence from counselor Helen Ely
    - Various groups/individuals pertaining to funding and community support, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 6)
    - Various organizations, 1943 (Folder 4: 7)
    - War Relocation Authority, 1942 August-1943 November (Folder 4: 8-14)
    - Wartime Civil Control Administration, 1942 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Young Mens/Women's Christian Association, 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 16)
  - Colleges, Universities, and Academic Professionals Correspondence, circa 1942-1943 (Folder 4)
    - A-N, circa 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 17)
    - O-Y, circa 1942-1943 (Folder 4: 18)
  - Student Correspondence, 1942-1946 (Folder 5)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1942-1946, undated (Folder 5: 1-5)
      Also includes excerpts from letters sent by students and letters pertaining to students
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1942-1944 January (Folder 5: 6-9)
    - Letters to students from colleges and universities, 1942-1943 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Miscellany Correspondence, 1942-1944, undated (Folder 5: 11)
  - Office Records and Procedures, 1942-1946 (Folder 5-6)
    - Administrative procedures, circa 1942 (Folder 5: 12)
    - College lists and information, circa 1942-1944 (Folder 5)
      - Approved colleges, circa 1942-1944 (Folder 5: 13)
        Includes lists of colleges approved by the Army and Navy
      - College information sheets, 1943 February-1944 January (Folder 5: 14-15)
      - Colleges submitted for and pending approval, circa 1942-1943 (Folder 6: 1)
      - Lists of colleges favorable to Japanese students, circa 1942-1943, undated (Folder 6: 2)
      - Lists of colleges with accepted Japanese students, circa 1942, undated (Folder 6: 3)
      - Statistics and information pertaining to student placement in colleges, circa 1942-1944, undated (Folder 6: 4)
        Includes map titled "Nisei students in colleges and universities outside restricted areas: 1941-1943"
    - Documents generated for or by NJASRC, circa 1942-1946 (Folder 6: 5)
      Includes "Final Audit of Japanese American Student Relocation Council, 1946", information regarding NJASRC projects and other statistics
    - Forms and pamphlets for student council use, 1942, undated (Folder 6: 6)
    - Minutes of meetings, 1942-1945 (Folder 6: 7)
      Includes minutes of Council meetings, 1944-1945, Plenary meeting, 1943, and Executive Committee meetings, 1942, 1945
    - Memoranda, circa 1942-1945 (Folder 6: 8)
      Includes memoranda sent between NJASRC staff, groups within NJASRC, and NJASRC as a whole
    - Newsletters, 1943-1944 (Folder 6: 9)
    - Reference and personal notes pertaining to students and/or NJASRC, circa 1942-1943 (Folder 6: 10)
    - Reports, 1943-1944 (Folder 6: 11)
    - Student lists, circa 1942-1943 (Folder 6: 12)
      Includes lists of students who have been either FBI or Department of War approved, accepted in college, which students have permits and which students are still waiting for permits
- Subject File and Collected Documents, 1942-1945 (Box 6-7)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1942-1945 (Folder 6: 13)
    Includes memoranda, monthly bulletins, and copies of Civil Liberties Quarterly
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1942-1945, undated (Folder 6: 14)
    Includes publications, information bulletins, memoranda, newsletters, and correspondence
  - Clippings, 1942-1943 (Folder 6: 15)
  - Committee on the Resettlement of Japanese Americans, 1945, undated (Folder 6: 16)
  - Executive Order #9066, 1942 February 19; Executive Order 9102, 1942 March 18; Text of White House Statement on Treatment of Persons of Japanese Ancestry, 1942-1943 (Folder 7: 1)
  - Extracts from the Testimony of J. Edgar Hoover Before the Subcommittee of the Committee of the Appropriations House of Representatives, 1943, February 18, Evidence of Americanism Among Japanese Americans, 1943, July 7 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Japanese American evacuation and relocation, 1942-1944, undated (Folder 7: 3)
    includes articles, pamphlets and small publications
  - Midget Tribune, 1944-1945 (Folder 7: 4)
  - O'Brien, Robert, 1943-1944 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Relocation center generated documents, 1943-1944 (Folder 7: 6-7)
    arranged alphabetically by relocation center
  - Statements regarding Japanese American loyalty, circa 1942-1943 (Folder 7: 8)
  - War Relocation Authority, 1942-1943 (Folder 7: 9-10)
  - Miscellany, 1943-1944; undated (Folder 7: 11)